Chihuahua Mexico Photograph Album 1906-1909
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Chihuahua, Mexico Photograph Album, 1906-1909
MS 238
Unknown
A family album of photos of places and people in Mexico, Colorado, and New England from 1906 to 1909. Notes by field historian Bernard L. Fontana, as well by the original compiler of the album, are quoted in the finding aid.
.2 linear feet.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Historical Note
Many of the over 600 small black and white photographs were taken in Mexico, mostly in Chihuahua. Subjects include mines, railroads, Tarahumara Indians and other local inhabitants, landscapes, street scenes, and mission churches. The other locations are various New England states and Colorado. The photographs have handwritten annotations below that often identify the places or people; many are of family and friends.
The family name is unknown, but they appear to have been from New England. At least one of the members was involved in mining ventures in Chihuahua, and possibly, Colorado.
Organization
This collection is organized chronologically in one album.
Photographs, 1906-1909
Access Terms
Tarahumara Indians -- Photographs.
Spanish mission buildings -- Mexico -- Chihuahua -- Photographs.
Chihuahua (Mexico: State) -- Social life and customs -- Photographs.
Mine buildings -- Mexico -- Santa Eulalia (Chihuahua) -- Photographs.
Chihuahua (Mexico: State) -- Photographs.
Santa Eulalia Mining Camp (Chihuahua, Mexico) -- Photographs.
Copper Canyon (Mexico) -- Photographs.
New England -- Social life and customs -- Photographs.
1900-1924
Container List
- Volume: Photographs, 1906-1909
  - Page 1
    Field Historian notes:
    Monterde is a mine in the municipio of Guazapares in central western Chihuahua near Sonora and Sinaloa and the head of the Río Septentrión, which in turn is a part of the headwaters of the Río Fuertre. The Monterde mineral deposits were discovered about 1844; the place takes its name from José Mariano Monterde, the 20th governor of Chihuahua.
    Tascates is one of the first named locations west of modern-day Creel on the route of today's Ferrocarril Chihuahua al Pacifico. It is between San Rafael and Areponapuchi.
    - (1) "Monterde Outfit, Earl Comstock, James S. Wyatt, mozo Jesús Vásquez. Pack mules. Taken on [Kansas City, Mexico & Orient Railway of Texas] grading near kilom. 50." April 2, 1906
    - (2) "Balance Rocks. Monterde-Tascates Trail, near El Cajon."
    - (3) "Buena Vista. Barranca de Cobre Canyon, 2 hours east of Tascates."
    - (4) "Balance rock near El Cajon. Earl Comstock on horseback."
  - Page 2
    The Kansas City, Mexico & Orient Railway was incorporated in Kansas in April, 1900 to connect Emporia, Kansas, with Topolobampo, Sinaloa. Track laying began east of Chihuahua City in 1902. The operation went bankrupt in 1912.
    Miñaca is the first town to the west of La Junta on the Ferrocarril Chihuahua al Pacifico. It is here that the tracks make a sharp turn toward the southwest as one comes from the east.
    - (1) "Miñaca. White tail deer on freight car [of Kansas City, Mexico & Orient]."
    - (2) "Monterde. View from no.2 tunnel looking northeast."
    - (3) "Buena Vista. Barranca de Cobre Canyon, 2 hours east of Tascates."
    - (4) "Monterde 'Sombrero.' Man on ladder is Josè Quesada y Cajon. Largest open workings on vein, El Carmen Vein."
  - Page 3
    "Buena Vista" is probably the location of modern-day Divisadero on the F.C. Chihuahua al Pacifico. If so, from this point on the northern edge of the Barranca del Cobre there is a panoramic view of the barrancas.
    Bocoyna is east of Creel about midway between Creel and San Juanita on the line of the Ferrocarril Chihuahua al Pacifico. The game the the women are playing is the "hoop-and-stick rice, " or "dowèrami." The race is described in B.L. Fontana's Tarahumara: where night is the day of the moon (Flagstaff: Northland Press, 1979, pp.98-99, 101-103).
    - (1) "Tarahumara Indians women 3 days' 'ring' race at Bocoyna, Sunday, March 19."
    - (2) "Monterde mill site's 'casa.'"
    - (3) "Buena Vista. Barranca del Cobre Canyon, 2 hours east of Tascates."
    - (4) "Gladys [Bogg] & 'Buster Brown.'"
  - Page 4
    The Indians working in the mine at Monterde are Tarhuamaras. The dancer, in spite of hat and trousers is probably a woman, and the dance a "yúmari" dance (see Fontana 1979: 57). Chinipas is in western Chihuahua near the Sonoran border, northwest of Alamos, Sonora.
    - (1) "Balance Rocks. Monterde-Tascates trail near El Cajon."
    - (2) "Trenchment in solid rocks on trail west of Bocoyna on old Chinipas-Chihuahua [trail] cut out by hoofs of mules & horses 6-10 ft. deep."
    - (3) "Monterde. March 26, Sunday. Indian dancing."
    - (4) "Monterde. No.1 lower tunnel."
  - Page 5
    - (1) "Bocoyna. [Tarahumara] Indian women in three day race [i.e. "dowèrami"].
    - (2) "Monterde Main no.2 tunnel. El Carmen Vein. Shows building & timber & tunnel entrance to left of group [of] workmen."
    - (3) "Monterde."
    - (4) "Tahamarie [Tarahumara] Indians racing along Monterde Creek. March 25, 1906. Sunday."
  - Page 6
    - (1) "Buena Vista or Barranca de Cobre Canyon 2 hours east of Tascates."
    - (2) "Tarahumarie [sic] Indians racing. Monterde. Sunday, 1906."
    - (3) "Tarahamari [sic] Indian boy on ranch near Tascates."
    - (4) "Monterde. No.3 tunnel. Upper Sombrero."
  - Page 7
    - (1) "Monterde. Main tunnel."
    - (2) "Tarahamarie [sic] Indians watching Sunday races. 1906."
    - (3) "Barranca [del Cobre] looking south."
    - (4) "Monterde. G. Wyatt, Camilo Esperno, Prof. Bogg. Mozo [servant] grinding samples of ore."
  - Page 8
    - (1) "Principal plaza opposite cathedral. Chihuahua [City]. Holiday trimmings."
    - (2) "Just before taking the launch ride across Lake Chapala."
    - (3) "Stage coach. 8 mules."
    - (4) "Gladys [Bogg], Mr. Schauffler, Grace, Papa on trip to Mexico City."
    - (5) "Street scene."
    - (6) "Mamma, Grace, & Mr. Earl Comstek [Comstock?]. Day we visited cemetery in front of long church."
    - (7) "Scene at railroad station. Selling. Musicians. Whistling. Pulque."
    - (8) "Beast of burden."
    - (9) "Mexican children begging at train for 'centavos.'"
  - Page 9
    The stagecoach belongs to the Batopilas Mining Company, a New York-based firm incorporated in October, 1887. An excellent account of taking this stage from Chihuahua into the Tarahumara country in 1889 is in Frederick Schwatcka, In the land of cave and cliff dwellers (Glorieta, New Mexico: Rio Grande Press, 1977: 133-171).
    - (1) "Tying spur on chicken. Mr. Murray took these six [pictures]. [Cock] fight I saw." April 6, 1906.
    - (2) "Teasing cock."
    - (3) "White lines. Ready for fight. Spur on legs."
    - (4) "Hard fighting, gambling on outside of ring."
    - (5) "Still fighting. Judge watching."
    - (6) "Most dead. Red one won. Both died from wounds."
    - (7) "At depot on Mexico City trip."
    - (8) "Old stage coach for crossing plain."
    - (9) "Big hat. Marketing, pottery & fruit."
  - Page 10
    - (1) "Gladys [Bogg] under banana tree in the hotel patio at Cuernavaca. March 23, 1906."
    - (2) "Home of natives in Chapala."
    - (3) "Mexican women drying washing on trees in Chapala. Sailboats and launches on lake."
    - (4) "Indians with working material on them. At top of fall near Indian pottery village near Cuernavaca."
    - (5) "House boat, thatched roof. Many on the canal that brings produce into city. On way to floating gardens [of Xochimilco]. Mexico City."
    - (6) "Swings [i.e. hammocks] & homes of Indians & Mexicans."
    - (7) "Rocks on Lake Chapala."
    - (8) "Old stage coach."
    - (9) "Mexicans pushing boat on way to Floating Gardens."
  - Page 11
    - (1) "Minnie directing Mr. Schauffler to take other point of land at Lake Chapala. Day we took our walk."
    - (2) "'Patio' at Cuernavaca, 75 miles south of Mexico City."
    - (3) "Indian women working on canal at Floating Gardens. Most filthy water."
    - (4) "Near Floating Gardens. Mexican home & children."
    - (5) "Near Guadalajara. Orange cart. Wooden wheels. Hard yoke. Cattle can't move heads."
    - (6) "In the market in Cuernavaca."
    - (7) "Lane at Chapala. Pulque plant [i.e. Agave] on rocks."
    - (8) "Mr. Schauffler talking Spanish to Indian woman for oranges. She knocked off with sugar cane."
    - (9) "Mexican whistling at train. Blind."
  - Page 12
    Santa Eulalia is a famed silver mine next to the modern-day Chihuahua City. It was begun in 1702, but because it had no water supply, a nearby town was established where there was water, a town which in time became Chihuahua City's great cathedral. The Santa Eulalia continues in production today, largely as a producer of lead and zinc. It is among the oldest continuously-working mines in the New World.
    - (1) "Rufus, Gladys [Bogg], Mr. Kitchens, and little lame Arthur."
    - (2) "Trail to Santa Eulalia."
    - (3) "Cathedral in Chihuahua [City]."
    - (4) "Santa Eulalia. Miners' homes."
    - (5) "Mex. hats."
    - (6) "Santa Eulalia mining camp."
    - (7) "Ox cart at depot."
    - (8) "Chihuahua mountains. Adobe houses."
    - (9) "Mamma on burro, Papa on horseback headed for Santa Eulalia."
  - Page 13
    The "Juárez 100 anniversary" refers to the 100th anniversary of the birth of Benito Juárez, a Zapotec Indian who became President of Mexico, on March 21, 1806. A "chicken ladder" is a ladder made by carving notches in a log.
    - (1) "Spanish carriage and decoration for Juárez 100 anniversary."
    - (2) "Cows on [?]. Miñaca, with Rufus and Papa."
    - (3) "Patio in Cuernavaca."
    - (4) "Ore train on mt. side on way to Santa Eulalia."
    - (5) "Mr. Schauffler from Kansas City."
    - (6) "Where 80 miners were buried. Went down in mine on chicken ladder."
    - (7) "Gladys [Bogg] & Mamma in Rufus' patio."
    - (8) "Bullfight ring" [probably Chihuahua City; see p.17, no.4].
    - (9) Mozo & Papa on horseback going to Santa Eulalia."
  - Page 14
    - (1) "Pulque plant field. Many near Mex. City."
    - (2) "Mexican pushing boat we rode in Floating Gardens on."
    - (3) "Men working. April. Santa Eulalia."
    - (4) "Home of Mexicans. Dog. Washing."
    - (5) "Indian carrying baby to sell things at train."
    - (6) "Street mule cars & cathedral on left in Chihuahua [crossed out] Mexico City." [Chihuahua City is more likely correct]
    - (7) "Indian dress & house & burro."
    - (8) "Parade day in Mexico City. Mexican on horseback. Juárez's 100 anniversary."
    - (9) "Market selling fruit."
  - Page 15
    The presumed "grave" on a hilltop is probably not a grave, but a rock cairn holding the "cruz mayor" for some nearby village and church.
    - (1) "Home on canal in Floating Gardens."
    - (2) "Mexican cross & grave of someone. Many such on mountain tops."
    - (3) "Market."
    - (4) "Wood brought many miles in Chihuahua."
    - (5) "Indians & home."
    - (6) "Ox team & Mexican horse. On way to Miñaca."
    - (7) "Way of carrying bundles. Always run. Mexico City."
    - (8) "Old stage coach."
    - (9) "Scene on street. Selling goods."
  - Page 16
    - (1) "Center of grave yard in Chihuahua [City]."
    - (2) [no caption]
    - (3) "Grace, Gladys [Bogg] in front of Juárez picture in Mexico City."
    - (4) "Graves in Chihuahua cemetery."
    - (5) "Colored bead piece over grave."
    - (6) "Cathedral in Chihuahua."
    - (7) "Mrs. Sawyers' little boy's grave."
    - (8) "Plaza in center in Chihuahua."
    - (9) "Grave in cemetery at Chihuahua."
  - Page 17
    - (1) "Turks' home on corner near church. Made of red brick."
    - (2) "Chihuahua Mt. on left. San Francisco church."
    - (3) "Way of carrying burdens on head."
    - (4) "Bull fight ring in Chihuahua."
    - (5) "Government building & soldiers on parade in Chihuahua."
  - Page 18
    - (1) "Horse & rocks in cut on trail."
    - (2) "Chihuahua & cathedral. Went up on top under bells. 94 ft. high."
    - (3) "Swallows on wire in Chihuahua."
    - (4) "Gladys [Bogg] & little girl on burro. Rufus holding reins."
  - Page 19
    - (1) "Ore train."
    - (2) "Guadalupe church. Place of... weddings"
    - (3) "Monterde. Main tunnel."
    - (4) "Barranca."
  - Page 20
    - (1) "Iron bars on all windows."
    - (2) "Guadalupe church."
    - (3) "Principal plaza on gala day."
    - (4) "Theatre or 'Teatro' as in Spanish. Built by government."
  - Page 21
    The Guadalupe church in Ciudad Juárez, Chihuahua, was founded as an Indian mission by the Franciscans in the late 17th century. It is famed for the hand-carved and decorated "vigas" in its roof. Nor should it be confused with the other Guadalupe church shown in some of the pictures. The latter may be in or near Chihuahua City.
    - (1) "Juárez. Guadalupe church. Plaza."
    - (2) "Mexican with pet cock in cock pit."
    - (3) "Mexican cattle. Longhorns."
    - (4) "Mexican women washing in river."
  - Page 22
    - (1) "Rocks on trail."
    - (2) "Cathedral in Chihuahua."
    - (3) "Rufus ready for trip to mts. Knife, pistol, gun."
    - (4) "Scene on railway track."
    - (5) "Chuhuahua and mts. in background."
  - Page 23
    - (1) "Mexican home on way to Miñaca."
    - (2) "Santa Eulalia Mining Company."
    - (3) "Public jail in Chihuahua."
    - (4) "Mexican ploughing with oxen."
  - Page 24
    - (1) "Guadalupe church. Place of fine weddings."
    - (2) "Market place."
    - (3) "Santa Eulalia mine."
    - (4) "Mr. Murray and party at Santa Eulalia. From Mr. Murray"
  - Page 25
    - (1) "Sorrel horse I rode. Named him Prince. Both Mr. Murray's."
    - (2) "Indian, pony & violin & jockeying outfit."
    - (3-5) "Mr. Murray's dog."
  - Page 26
    - (1) "Milk men in Chihuahua."
    - (2) "Mr. Murray to left of group. Party he was with at Santa Eulalia."
    - (3) "Indians with bow and arrows."
    - (4) "Government building & cathedral in Chihuahua."
  - Page 27
    - (1) "Palace Hotel and bank building in Chihuahua."
    - (2) "Mr. Murray and Indian in Chihuahua. Indian dressed as they come into town. Iron bars on windows."
    - (3) "Indian dress and hat & dog."
    - (4) "Palace Hotel & plaza. Building to right torn down."
  - Page 28-30
    Various scenes in Colorado: Colorado Springs, Cripple Creek, some mining property, etc.
  - Page 31-34, September, 1906
    All photographs from Mr. Murray at Murray's mine in Chihuahua.
  - Page 34-53, August 1906-summer 1907.
    All family photographs; some in Colorado but most in various places in New England (Maine and Massachusetts).
  - Page 54-84
    More Mexico scenes, nearly all of them in Chihuahua, and including a few duplicates of earlier pictures. All fairly well labeled or otherwise self-explanatory when compared to earlier pictures.
    Mission San Miguel Arcángel de Oposura, which after 1828 became Moctezuma, Sonora, Mexico. Mission historian George Eckhart believed the bell tower collapsed in the 1887 earthquake, but this picture, and that of the same church on p. 81 (3), are probably contemporaneous with others in the album. This would suggest he was wrong and that its collapse occurred after 1906.
    - p.66 (4) "Mr. Comstock Sunday a.m. on trip, trying to convert Mexican..."
    - p.76 (2) Mission Santa Barbara, California.
    - p.76 (3) Guadalupe church, Juárez, Chihuahua.
    - p.77 (1) Mission San Miguel Arcángel de Oposura.
  - Page 82 -end of album
    All family pictures, Colorado and New England.